Let's shortly discuss the differences
the main life-cycle
inventory database.
The largest database is
mostly used is
Ecoinvent database.
We have spoken of
it quite a bit.
Developed by different
research institutions
from the Swiss government.
The European platform on
life-cycle assessment
has developed
a product environmental
footprint
which is really interesting.
You access most of the data of
these via the Life
Cycle Initiative
website we've just looked at.
In terms of the US.
US has not long tradition of
inventory process LCA data,
but has a long tradition of
economic base data
input output data.
I will shortly introduce you,
what it is about.
We have data for 400 sector and
this is also accessible
within Simapro.
You can access, it's
usually under the name of
the C database that you need to
upload when you upload
your different database.
This is an interesting one to
upload and have it
in your database.
Now you have also a
whole series of sector
specific database and that
includes the
Agrifootprint database,
which is also in Simapro.
The Agribalyse that you
also have in Simapro
all via the GLAD network and
the World Food Database
from the company
you created Quantis
which you can.
In fact, is now incorporated
mostly in Ecoinvent
itself or accessible
via the EU platform.
Finally, in the LCA you
have the LCA commons,
which is a nice
datasets developed by
USDA here and the
National Library.
The problem is it's
relatively difficult to do
an entire LCA on these
LCA commons because
the data are not always complete
and you have to be very
careful that you don't have
missing processes when
you use these data,
but they can be nice to
incorporate in a sense
within another database.
Other main developer of data,
country are Japan,
China is coming,
which is nice to have first
dataset from China, Korea,
and Australia, which also
important data
producer, I would say.
Let's now go a bit more in
detail in the
Ecoinvent database.
It's the broadest unit
process database worldwide,
has energy system
material and building,
chemical metals, transport,
packaging, waste treatment,
agriculture, and quite a
few electronics product
that I really need to
have like a laptop,
a printer, screen, flat,
or different types of screen.
It's the latter
that you have here.
For each of the process,
you will get 400 inventory
flow time, 4,000 processes.
This is a lot of
data to analyze,
but it's really precious
because that gives
you the basis and
the background processes
for many of your data.
Two things I want to
say on this databases.
First, it's good
because the people who
have created it are
hyper systematic.
It's a bit of a
question of culture.
They are here, Swiss,
German, super detailed,
super systematic,
able to what I call
"Answer the call for
data" like a monk,
nearly where you are able to
study a process
during a long time.
Get all the data from
the literature or from
online data and check
what is there in the team
would have loved that.
They would always have
one institute who
was responsible for a set
of data, for example,
for energy system or
material building and to
other people, at least,
from other institutes checking
the quality of the
data so it was check,
check, check and really
high-quality data.
In fact, the early
database started in
1996 on energy system,
environment the database
became in early 2000s,
the Ecoinvent come
and we are now
the third version
of this database.
I trust in fact,
data via people I
know are systematic.
I know them personally
or [inaudible] who
developed that earlier
is good friend.
I can trust what he's doing
in term of the quality
of what is that.
I was part of this
Ecoinvent center
in the bulge coming from the
[inaudible] on the French-speaking
part of Switzerland.
My main contribution,
it was not on data.
My main contribution is
I forced them to write
in English because they
were documenting
things in German.
I said no way
you do it in English.
Your database is the most
important in the world.
You need every process to
be documented and you have
three folders of about
a foot of paper,
which is now also
of course in PDF,
which is available to support
and document the data.
That's really a
great initiative.
How did they develop it.
It was very interesting.
The people first did
some energy system under
the guidance of a professor
that in fact I had
in my own studies.
They did that and
from there onwards,
they made a joint venture
with the Swiss EPA.
The EPA was smart because
instead of trying to finance
everything themselves,
they contacted the Swiss office
for material and building,
the Swiss office
for transportation,
for agriculture.
Each of these offices,
like USDA for agriculture but
the equivalent for Switzerland,
finance, a part of the database.
As a whole, it costed,
the first run was probably
about three million dollars.
That's probably another three
million or even more which
have been invested in
the meantime to develop
all these data and we
can access it for,
I think, $1,500 or
something like that,
this order of magnitude.
But you have access to
it through Simapro here.
Through the software
that we will be using.
Ecoinvent database provide
all flows at two level,
at the units process level and
then direct emission
and extraction.
Plus you get in fact the
intermediary flow when you have
the unit process level.
Intermediary are really
only for unit process.
Whereas instead of
the U for UP level,
you also have
systems level flows
which are aggregated
inventory emissions.
I would say that if you
are using and developing,
adapting a process unit,
process level is really neat.
If you need to adapt it.
If you're just
using it, in fact,
is much easier to
visualize afterwards if
you directly use the
aggregated because
behind it you will
have thousands of processes this
is sometimes hard to visualize.
If you have no change,
I would recommend
that you apply that.
Especially because in the
version we have excess,
we cannot do the
uncertainty analysis
directly where the
uncertainty you
need your UP level here.
Many other database only provide
aggregated flows in that case.