The ecoinvent database provide
these two types of data.
It provides unit process level.
These are processes which
are called with U,
which have the detail of
direct elementary flow
and intermediary.
It means with any data
you always account
for the 4,000 other
processes to get it.
It's complicated, but you
have a high level of detail,
which is really nice
when you want to just
modify one of these process.
You just modify
exactly what you want
and you can rerun it
and get your results.
The second level, which is
easier to use and I recommend,
I would say that you use
the system level by
default when you will
work on SimaPro.
It's the aggregated
elementary flow that you have
for a given product summed
up over the entire supply chain.
No intermediary flow here,
only total elementary flow
per functional unit or
per kilo of the commodity
that we are defining.
Many other databases don't
have the same resolution,
only offer aggregated flow,
which is problematic because
you cannot modify them easily.
So you have to ask the
people who've done
the data to modify them,
which some company like to keep
their customer
dependent on them,
but personally and in
our quantities company,
we are trying to affect
our customer independence.
They will need us because
we didn't need to be
always cutting edge and
we'll have the next ID.
Such aggregate
inventory flow for
different processes can
be directly used to build
the inventory of new
products and we see with
a car example how
once you have these
aggregated system level flow,
you can use them
relatively easy,
even Excel spreadsheet to build
the impact of a given
product so in summary,
the inventory phase
of the LCA determine
the elementary flow or
emission and extraction
per functional unit.
Accounting for the
entire processes
which contribute to
the project function.
The inventory is
calculating by combining
the intermediary flow
per functional unit and
the elementary flow per unit of
the same unit process to get the
total per functional
unit at each level.
So it's important that we don't
mix the intermediary direct
and the aggregated
elementary flow
over our products system.
Finally, the good news
is that we have a lot
of inventory data.
The bad news is correcting
even one process for
inventory data on
the intermediary and
elementary flow is
really hard work.
So you need direct
contact with company,
or you need to go
in the literature,
it's pretty hard work.
But the beauty is we have
a lot of processes
which are existing.
We can rely on that and
just do it for what is
needed as a complement
to what we already have.