Let us look together at
guidelines for
performing the Phase 2
of your case study leading
to the final
presentation and using
SimaPro software for calculating
your impact assessment
and interpretation.
The learning objective
here is for Phase 2,
to use the SimaPro
software focusing on
impact assessment and
interpretation of your results.
In addition to your
presentation and accounting for
the command received after
your final presentation,
you want to write a two-pages
concise and rich abstract
with main results.
Here I would like to provide you
an overview of the
different instructions,
template, example, deliverables,
and evaluation criteria
for case study.
Phase 2. We focus on Phase 2
as the use of the SimaPro
software leading to
final presentation
and to a summary of
two pages which summarize your
main methods and results.
What are the
objectives of Phase 2?
Compare and interpret
the comprehensive
environmental impacts,
this time not just
CO_2 energy balance,
but acidification,
eutrophication,
all the different impact of
your product alternatives
using an LCA software,
and you can also perform
some sensitivity study here.
You want to collect the data for
the selected variables from
Phase 1 to improve what you
had done in screening
and you want to
provide recommendation
for product improvements.
What are the steps and
deliverable of Phase 2?
After a first run and
implementing results
in new software,
we'll take a first process T for
CO_2 energy and GA1 results and
compare it with the
energy and CO_2
from GA1 results from your
previous hand calculation.
We want to compare
software results with
hand calculation.
This is your group
activity 2a deliverable.
You then perform the inventory
and impact assessment,
accounting for the commands
that we will make after
that you have presented here
your first process tree,
and that will lead
for the slides for
your final case
study presentation
posted on the day before
your presentation for it.
The final slide will include
correction from the
oral presentation
that you will have received.
In GA4, you have
these final two-pages projects
abstract including two figures.
Let's go a bit more in
detail what it looks like.
For group activity 2a,
the process tree and
inventory, basically,
you implement your scenario in
SimaPro following the guidelines
and the experience we got
with hands trying
example together,
performing it together
this time on your own you
will do it and implement
your scenario.
Be careful to really
design your process,
not everything per
functional units
all the time and have one
assembly with everything.
You want to create
components like we created
for the towel in the
hands drying example,
we create one towel which
include the transport
of that towel,
the paper used for that towel,
and even the disposal
for that towel.
Then in the assembly
you will say,
I'm using 1.5 towel
per functional unit.
The interest of that is if you
can easily perform a
sensitivity study,
if I'm using one or two
towel or three towels,
what are the changes,
and you can very easily run
this scenario in that way.
You can also verify things in
an easy way if you do
it per components.
We want here now to display
the fossil CO_2 and the
non-renewable primary energy.
Take it from impact 2002,
for example, Tracy,
you cannot really
compare with the CO_2
with its surplus energy,
which doesn't account for
the main energy consumption,
so you take it in Impact 2002
and you perform the
network and process tree,
and you compare your
process tree with
your hand and excel calculation
that you made earlier,
explain any
substantial difference
more than, for example,
30 percent because that's
probably is why you
have a problem.
We have posted here
a template which
enable you to make that and
post your different points.
This is a good example with
the wall paint compared
to a wallpaper.
Here for the wall paint,
for each scenario,
you want to look at
the process tree,
identifying the main
contributors here that we
have and you compare
then the amount of
CO_2 you have here with the
amount you had calculated
by hand calculation
and you should be
relatively close
normally within 10,
20, maximum 30 percent,
but if 30 percent, you
start to need to explain.
By the way, you
could still detail
in SimaPro that you have
about 61 percent
for the Ti0_2 here,
the titanium dioxide here
20.5 percent and AU steel,
which is the last five
percent that you have here.
Do that for each
of the scenario.
Then that will constitute
your first GA2a deliverable.
In GA2b, you want
then to present
your normalized damage
per impact category.
Click on the top here you
have a small box to call,
which is per impact category
that you can click to
get not a total human
health impacts,
but the different impacts for
all the human health category
if you take here
for impact 2002,
and all the ecosystem
quality category,
the global warming and the
energy category
that you have here.
You can also perform in there
a sensitivity study looking
here at an alternative
wallpaper and
an alternative wall
paint that we have
here and looking what
are the improvement
if I have a product improvement
and you see here you
have a 30 percent
product improvement.
The beauty of keeping that
bearing per category is,
for example, you see
ionizing radiation
behaves slightly
differently from the other.
Some of the results are inverse
but we see here that this is
not really relevant here,
what is really relevant is
fine particulate matter,
a bit the carcinogen and
basically global warming and
non-renewable energy are
re-dominant in this case.
Evaluation criteria for
your final presentation,
we will look at the
quality of check between
your SimaPro inventory and
your hand calculation.
The originality and the interest
of impact assessment results,
the appropriate analysis and
depths of results
interpretation,
and the quality of
your conclusion and
especially recommendation
to the user
that what you've done
is directly useful.
We value the amount
of work you make
and the originality if
you take self-initiative,
not just what we told you
to do or classical case,
but explore a bit,
try new things.
This is how we learn
and we arrive to
interesting results.
We look at the quality of
your presentation and ability to
answer question to arrive
to an overall rate.
The grade themselves will
be put at the end of GA3b.
Once you have resubmitted
your presentation with
the corrected slides,
then we will
evaluate that in one
go the other intermediate
representations so that you get
feedback as we progress
and you can correct
yourself and arrive to a really
good final presentation.
Then after the presentation,
accounting also for the
comments you have received,
you write a two-page summary
and we will provide you a
template for that which
is in fact coming
from the template to
propose abstract for the
C Tech Europe Conference,
which is a nice, instead
of just being 400 words,
it's two pages
template where you
can define your introduction
and goal definition,
method data inventory here.
Don't tell so much what you
did but how you did it.
Say, we used this and
this two to obtain this,
or we applied this
model to do that,
not just that we did that.
We want to understand
well how you did it.
Then for the results on
impact assessment and
discussion interpretation,
we want here all main result.
Again, don't say we
obtained CO_2 balance.
You give the results
of your CO_2 balance,
the results of your network.
For that, we want you
to paste two figures
and have some legends and
labeled clearly displayed.
X axis must have
units and clearly
indicated on these two figures
and choose the one
which are risks,
which summarizes, in a sense,
all UK studying in
a compact way but
informative way and
be result-oriented.
Present what is original,
what you bring you.
Here, finally,
have also short recommendation
of what you say
plus a few references with
your main sources that you use.
Evaluation criteria for
the final abstract.
The method is clearly
and shortly summarized,
including the main data sources.
Results are correct.
We want no mistake,
especially because
you got feedback
so you should be good now,
well-described and a good
interpretation of figures.
It's not just putting a figure.
You need to get out the
information or the figure,
interpret what are
the main influence,
what is interesting
in this figure,
in a few bullet points
that you can have.
We value the adequate choices
of the two main figure,
that they are really the best
results and that you have
useful recommendation with
future work and
short limitation.
Again, amount of work,
originality and
self-initiative and
the quality of the writing.
We want it concise and
rich informative test
in a professional layout.
Finally, we'll arrive
to an overall rating.
To help you to perform all this,
we have a few complimentary
file for GA2a.
The process tree,
you have a process
tree template file.
We provide you an example of
the final presentation on this
wallpaper and wall paint,
which was well-designed
project here.
You have two pages abstract
template which is empty
and you can fill it in,
and you have an abstract
example, again,
which was from an
interesting project
that you can look at.