How old or I should say,
how young is
life-cycle assessment
as a method than the science?
We'll look and recognize that
the history of LCA
and LCA standard is
relatively recent and has been
rapidly evolving and
progressing at the same time.
We want you to be able to list
the main LCA standards or
LCA-based standards that we
will refer to in this class.
A short historical
review of LCA.
The first LCA has been done
1969 on beverage
packaging by Coca-Cola.
In fact, with a strong
interest in solid waste.
And it's interesting that we
started with waste in LCA.
Is it because waste is
the most important
program in the world?
No, probably not.
But it's what we see is
what is left in our
hands when we've
consume our product and
that we don't really need.
That's why the focus
started with that.
The Swiss EPA produced
several studies
on packing material which
were very good basis
and starting basis for then
evolve to other studies
because they had all
different type of
energy production
mostly for packing,
or they had all the
different material
they had collected the data for.
The first restructuring of
LCA came through the
SETAC code of practice,
a small documents from Peston
workshop with experts.
And that was developed by
the SETAC Society for
Environmental Toxicology
and Chemistry,
which is historically
the society who has and
continues to develop LCA with
conferences bringing
together every year
about 200 scientists working
on this method
development in the world.
This SETAC so then to show
the different working
group from 1995-1999,
which really led to
further structure the method
and serves as a basis for
an important milestone which was
the first ISO standards
that was determined there.
At the end of the 90s,
you know scientists
how they are.
They like to work together,
but they like their own
methods, their own approach.
To really arrive to
recommendation and help
as a practitioner,
we thought we need
an outside partner
beyond the scientific
society like SETAC.
With my colleague,
we were heading in
fact the group on
impact assessment and
we thought let's contact
the United Nations
Environmental Program UNEP,
and to see if they would
collaborate and by chance,
when we contacted
them, Kofi Annan,
the UN Secretary at that
time had just called for
studying on the
environmental impact of
the entire supply chain so
we were just at the right time.
2002 we launch, with UNEP the
life-cycle initiative which
is still continuing and arriving
now at what we were
aiming at 20 years ago,
which was to arrive to
recommending an impact
assessment method.
But in between came a
very important progress
2003, the ecoinvent database,
which is one of the
largest database or
the largest database
with 4,000 processes at
the level of unit processes is
made available here or
mostly in Switzerland,
but with adaptation nowadays
in different countries.
In parallel with
the inventory side,
we have different impact
assessment method
like for toxicity USEstox,
ReCiPe is a Dutch method,
Impact World+ is our own method
developed with the Polytechnique
Montreal in Canada.
The effort of the
life-cycle initiative here,
which is they've logged
on LCIA guidance,
where we had two of these
framing workshop in
the last four years and we
are aiming at arriving as I say,
at the recommended reading
practices and methods.
In short, there has been
a lot of progress in
terms of data availability
for life-cycle inventory,
your life is much simpler than
mine when I started LCA to do
that and in life cycle
impact assessment,
which are available.
What are the standard available,
which are life-cycle based
or life-cycle related.
ISO has a whole series,
and this is a 14,000 series
of environmental standards.
In fact, relatively
surprising way
regarding the newness
of the approach,
LCA has been one of
the first environmental
management standard
here with two standards, 14040,
which was principal
and framework,
which gives a frame
then which is
developed within 14044,
which is the one you
want to look if you have
really detailed question
or need guidance for that.
Though they give guidance,
they don't give factors,
they don't give number.
That's the work in the
life-cycle initiative
to provide these more detailed,
harmonized method and numbers.
But it helps avoiding a
lot of the misuse of LCA.
If an LCA is ISO compatible,
it ensure basic
quality of the LCA.
2014, a water footprint
is developed,
which is really
life-cycle based,
headed by one of
my former collaborator,
Sebastian Harbor,
who had the process
for giving this
water footprint
LCA-based approach.
Two other standard shortly 14048
is giving some data
documentation and 14049,
our example of application
for this goal and scope and
the inventory analysis.
No ISO standard for
carbon footprint but there
is a product life cycle,
greenhouse gas accounting
and reporting practice from
the World Resources
Institute and
the World Business Council
on Sustainable Development.
In short, life-cycle assessment,
what the feature or
the main feature,
it relates the environmental
impact to the product,
service, or the function.
We've seen with the
popcorn example,
how we need to relate
not to just kilogram,
but to look at what is
a product function and have
a unit like the cubic meter use,
which is representative of
a function of a backing,
which is protecting and
transporting material.
With LCA, we quantify
mass balance of
emission of resources over
the whole life cycle
from cradle to grave,
or even cradle to cradle when
we have recycling
in our life cycle,
and we cover multiple
impacts: greenhouse effect,
toxicity resources
that we look at,
not only a single aspect,
like carbon or water here.
We have the four phases of LCA,
goal and scope, inventory,
impact assessment
interpretation that we will
go further in more detail
in the following chapters.
In summary, LCA is
relatively recent,
but has been rapidly
evolving and progressing
and maturing.
I would say we are
in a place which is
amazing compared to where
we were 30 years ago,
leading to standardization and
a large data availability,
which may make it
much easier to apply.
One of the first tool that
has been standardized,
and we have to
recognize a standard
only provide a frame
for good practice,
but not necessarily the method
or consensus methods that
could help making results
more consistent
across different LCA,
and that are needed to be
as a complement to
the ISO standards.
Also, we need to be sure
that the quality of
data is recognized and
ensured in all LCAs.