We know that getting
new data for life cycle
inventory is hot,
so could we benefit
from existing data to
get an easy way to obtain
the first order of magnitude
for many different product?
This is exactly
what input-output
LCA economic-based
LCA is offering.
The learning objectives are
to introduce the economic-based
input-output LCA
and apply this
economic input-output
LCA to the hand-dryer
example to show
you how you can perform
quickly an LCA on this basis.
Process LCA, we know,
is based on technical
coefficient and
detailed process modeling
for core processes.
If we take the
example of aluminum,
one of the main physical
flow for aluminum are
the kilowatt-hour electricity
used per kilogram aluminum.
What we're basically
doing in process LCA
is multiplying
these intermediary
physical flow by an
elementary flow of CO_2,
for example, per physical units,
so in kilo CO_2 per
kilowatt-hour electricity.
When we multiply that,
the kilowatt-hour electricity
goes away and we get
the kilo CO_2 per kilo aluminum.
That will be one of the
inventory flow that we have.
Now, economic
input-output-based LCA
rely on data which are
coming on the spending
of each sector.
We say, for example,
for one unit output
of this sector here,
this sector will spend money
in another two sectors.
For example, this
sector at tier 1,
will then spend amount of
money in other sector at tier 2.
We continue like
that up to infinity.
The beauty is any industry
from a sector is defacto
reporting to the Bureau
of Economic Analysis in
the US how much spending
they make in 400 sectors.
We can start building
this network for
400 different types of
products or commodities,
or sectors.
We can have either
commodity or sector based.
How does it work?
Instead of an intermediary
physical flow,
we have now an intermediary
economic flow,
which are the dollars
spent on buying
electricity per dollar
aluminum output
or aluminum produce.
What we need is determine
elementary flow per dollar,
per economic units
in, for example,
kilo CO_2 per
dollar electricity,
to multiply that,
and then the dollar
electricity go away,
and we get kilo CO_2
per dollar aluminum,
which will be our
new inventory flow.
If we multiply that
by the number of
dollar aluminum per
functional unit,
we will get the kilo CO_2
per functional unit.
The same way that here,
we were multiplying by
the kilo aluminum
per functional unit,
and we were getting
the same kilo CO_2
per functional unit
in both approaches.
Similar approaches, how do we
get the kilo CO_2 per
dollar electricity?
We, in fact, take the
overall electricity sector,
look at how many dollar output
we have from electricity,
what is the total CO_2 emission
from the electricity sector,
and do the relative ratio
of it to calculate this.
Let's take an example
and use a small tool which
is available online.
I invite you to also connect on
this website and we will
do it directly using it.
We can use the economic
input-output and
also identify which sector
has a dominant contribution.
Let's look how it works.
When you arrive to
www.eiolca.net,
this economic input-output
life cycle assessment.
You go and use the tool,
and you arrive here.
You can choose different
model of producer.
Let's stick to the
US 2002 Producer.
But we could have also a
purchaser perspective,
if you like, for
different years.
But this one has 428 sectors.
We can put here and
search for a product.
We had bought a computer
which was $1,585.
If we look for electronics,
and we search for it,
electronic computer,
you see we get different
computer and we
have here an electronic
computer manufacturing.
I would like to select that.
In addition, I will select a
million dollar in that case.
Here we had not a
million dollar,
but we'll keep in million
because if we take it in dollar,
we likely to have small coma,
which is not very convenient.
I put $1.585 million,
we'll have to divide the
results afterwards by 1,000.
Let's look first at
the economic activity
as outputs which will be
what economic activity this
$1.5 million in the computer
sector is creating.
You see that we get
here a higher economic
activity of $3.91
million for $1.5 million
spent in the electronic
computer and manufacturing.
Where is it spent?
Still, the highest number
is in the electronic
computer manufacturing.
But you see that wholesale
trade is important.
Printed circuits, management
of company is important,
computer storage, computer
terminal, semiconductor,
and then software is important,
scientific research
and development
services, and real estate.
We see the money is spent
in all these sectors.
One dollar spent in
one sector will generate
an additional number of
dollar in the rest
of the economy
through the different tiers.
Now we can change
the input and say,
I'm not interested so much
in the economic activity.
I'm not an economist.
But as an environmental person,
I'm interested in
greenhouse gases,
and we select that.
Now we've done an LCA
in a few minutes.
We have now the
greenhouse gases,
which are for $1.585 million.
What are the amount
of greenhouse gases?
Four hundred and
fifty one ton CO_2.
If I take now one
computer and divide
this million dollar by
1,000, this will be,
in fact, 451 kilogram
CO_2 per computer.
Where do we have
the main emission?
Power generation and supply,
that's the electricity.
Electricity for
manufacturing because
here we don't have the use
phase of the computer.
To add the use phase,
we should add a
certain amount of
dollars spent in the
electricity sector
during the use phase.
But already, the
power generation
and supply is dominant
for the manufacturing.
Then iron and steel mills,
oil and gas transportation.
You see truck transportation.
What is really interesting is
air transportation is here.
Even if it was not appearing in
the dollar spent because
of the high emission,
it comes out here in that case.
Even the wholesale
which is that trade,
which is not very energy
intensive or CO_2 intensive,
appears because of its
high contribution.
The beauty of that
is we have done
an LCA in a few minutes
and we have seen what are
the main contributor that we
can check if they
were included when I
do my process LCA of these, too.