Now that we know
how to aggregate
the different
elementary flow across
the entire supply chain and
get aggregated results,
I would say cradle to gate
for different material,
it's very interesting to
compare the primary energy
we are getting or
the CO_2 emission.
But to do that,
we first need to define well,
what type of energy
because there are
several term which are used
for describing the energy.
We want to define as a
learning objective primary,
final, and useful energy.
Second, we will then compare
aggregated processes
for primary energy
for various materials
and processes.
Let's look at this definition.
Primary energy is
defined as the energy
contained in the energy carrier
at the point of extraction.
It's the total energy
you extract from
the environment and that will
include the upstream
energy usage
that you need to
do the extraction,
to do the refinery,
the preparation, and to
distribute all that.
You need to extract
all that so that
you have the final
energy which is
delivered to the consumer or
purchased by the consumers if
we take his or her
point of view.
The final energy is what is
consumed whereas the
primary energy is
what needs to be extracted to
deliver this energy consumed.
The useful energy
is the portion of
the final energy
which is actually
delivered inside the
house for example,
or available after
final conversion
for the respective
use of the consumer.
Let's look at an example
to understand that.
Let's take natural gas first.
We have here some
gas and I buy one
megajoule final which
is at my gas meter.
First, what's happening
when you have a heating,
usually you have a
small stack on the roof
and you in fact are
ejecting some heat.
The efficiency will be
a key parameter here
which will relate the final
energy to the useful energy.
For a gas heater it has
a recuperation of condensation
which most of
modern heater have,
you get a high efficiency.
You can get like 95
percent efficiency so
one megajoule final,
0.95 megajoule useful.
How much energy do you
need to produce that?
You might have a tanker
or the pipeline,
have some losses
on the pipeline,
you need to transport that.
You will have order of magnitude
1.2-1.25 megajoule primary
per megajoule final.
Now let's move to electricity.
One megajoule final,
how much in the house?
Hundred percent.
Everything degrade in heat.
You get here one
megajoule useful,
so great, 100 percent
efficiency for the electricity.
That's pretty good.
Now, what upstream
from the electricity?
The electricity is high exergy,
high-quality and we
measure the quality of
energy in exergy which is
the potential to create
mechanical energy
with this energy.
Electricity has more than
95 percent potential
for creating the
mechanical work,
much higher than heat.
But that means that
when you want to
transform heat into high exergy,
you have losses and
substantial losses.
In fact, we are heating
the part at either
nuclear power station,
gas power station,
or coal power station;
you have these big
towers and you will lose
about 2/3 in the
atmosphere or you
have your longer
lake or river and
you will heat fishes in that
case and heat the water.
One megajoule final,
3.4 mega joule primary
are necessary.
Who was saying that for
heating electricity is
a good idea and efficient
because in fact,
it's a ratio of 3.4:1?
Again approximately 1.3:
1 delivered in the house.
The gas is much more
efficient and should
be kept for heating,
whereas electricity should
be kept for producing
mechanical work in cars
or different application
in our case.
Now, electricity
is often expressed
not in mega joule but
in kilowatt hour final.
That's what usually you buy.
As you have 3,600
seconds and a joule
is watt times second,
we have in fact,
one kilowatt-hour final
is 3.6 megajoule final.
One kilowatt-hour final,
one kilowatt-hour useful but
in terms of primary energy,
this will be in fact
3.4 and these are
megajoule primary per
megajoule final time
the 3.6 we have
here which is megajoule final
per kilowatt-hour final.
When you get that,
you get 3.4 times 3.6,
this is equal to 12.1 mega joule
primary energy per kilowatt-hour
final in that case.
You have to be really
careful that we always say
what type of energy
we are using.
What are the typical values for
different ores or
energy vectors,
energy carrier that
you have available?
We have a whole survey
which is around 40 here.
Down here kerosene,
light fuel, heavy fuel oil.
The oil-based material
are around 42,
43 megajoule per kilo,
relatively high density,
higher than for example,
the bio-gas or the
hard coal or the lower
quality coal which is even
lower here which can be
even lower than 10
megajoule per kilogram.
This is useful. When we want to
calculate the primary energy,
we will take the amount of
crude oil extracted and
multiply by this value,
and that will give us
this total megajoule
primary energy extracted.