Let's give you a slightly
more in-depth view
of these individual methods
looking shortly
at the framework.
LCIA Impact 2002+,
if you use it, it's
still relatively valid.
One important thing is
that it has damaged
category or area of
protection, the human health,
the ecosystem quality,
the resources,
but we had kept climate change
as a separate category.
Now when we move
to IMPACT World+,
what we did is we start to do
the modeling of the impact
of climate change on
the biodiversity,
and on human health,
and that IMPACT World+
is considering that.
But at that time in 2002,
we thought we were not
accurate enough to
go and cover the anti-storage.
IMPACT World+ you've
seen the method applied
to the kgeq study,
the front-end panel.
It was based on 2002 here,
but it provides now factor for
each continent, and allow
some regional assessment
which is important,
especially for the water
use and for acidification.
For example, it depends a lot
where you emit and what are
the quality of the soil
or the amount of water
scarcity in the region.
It was the first
implementation of
the USEtox model,
and also having
a water use impact included
in a full LCIA method.
Major improvement in
modeling land use,
water, and resource use.
For acidification and
eutrophication it has
world atmospheric and world
hydrological fate model
to really study this
in a special way.
The respiratory effects,
the fine particulates have
new intake fraction, and use
the GBD, epidemiological
derived factor.
When interests of
IMPACT World+ is that
you can base your
assessment on the area of
protection or on the
area of concern that our
carbon footprint and the
water footprints here.
In a compatible way
and consistent way,
you can look at
these two aspects.
ReCiPe goes the whole way
through from my life-cycle,
inventory results
to the results in
midpoint category to then go to
a damage or an endpoint
for human health,
ecosystem resources, and
eventually to a single score.
One originality of
ReCiPe is to have
a cultural perspective, and
three different cultural
individualistic.
Honesty, I don't know why they
incorporated that because if
you're individualist
you don't do LCIA.
You're just looking at what
is in your back garden,
and you don't mind life-cycle.
That's my own bias.
The two which are
really interesting,
the hierarchical methods.
The hierarchical methods will
consider mostly certain
prove with certain impacts.
You need to be proven
to be incorporated.
Whereas the third thing,
which is egalitarian,
you have more protective
perspective to say,
we take everything, best
estimate of all impact
whereas they are really observed
or their potential and accepted.
This is especially
valid for the toxicity.
Here we have all impacts
considered in that case.
The default one is
your hierarchical.
If you run it by default,
this is the one people
usually suggest.
TRACI. Tragedy
consistent methods.
Well-designed.
Doesn't have the damage as
a PT they haven't
moved to there.
For the cancer and non-cancer,
they also have been
using USEtox in
the latest revision of
2011 and we worked
in collaboration with
Jane Bear for that.
LCIA guidance Volume 1.
This was this workshop from
the UN and it's an ongoing work,
but Volume 1 had
the greenhouse gas,
particulate matter,
water use, land use.
The footprint indicator
recommendation
that we saw at the
start of this class,
were coming also
from this report.
Two years later, the second
workshop we had:
acidification, eutrophication,
ecotoxicity, human toxicity,
the soil quality and
some mineral resources.
I say we are now working
on the third level.
Here we had all our indicator,
which were for single category
and probably one of
the most interesting
indicator which was
developed at that time was
the aware
characterization factor
for available water
remaining methods.
The idea is to say we
have our characterization
factor or impact is
a function of the inverse of
the water remaining because
the less water you
have available,
the highest your water
scarcity and your problems.
How do we get this
water remaining?
This is the availability from
rainwater minus the demand,
and the demand has
two different part.
One is human consumption.
This is very clear.
The second is
a minimum environmental
requirements to keep
the biodiversity
in a river if you
reuse the flow too much
because you construct a dam,
there won't be any fish,
so there is a minimum
requirement in the region.
In addition, the CF
are limited when you
look at that between
0.1 and 100;
100 being the max scarcity
that we can have.
This indicator here,
what I like is to
divide it by the mass
scarcity to take this CF
divided by 100 and it expresses
the water scarcity level in
the watershed as a
fraction of the maximum,
which would be 100
cubic meter meter
world equivalent in that case.
Where do we see high water
scarcity in the world?
Not surprising, west coast
here of US and Mexico.
We have of course
the Arabic country
and Sahara region in Africa.
Then in fact, in Central Asia,
we have up to China,
a lot of desertic area.
Finally, to have
the Australia where you
have water in the coast,
but most of the other
area are relatively dry.
You see that depending on
where you are you count that
one cubic meter is equivalent to
0.01 cubic meter
in the blue zone,
but will be equivalent up
to 100 cubic meter average
or I would say if you
divide here by a hundreds,
that's why I prefer.
That will be you have an
index which go to basically
0-1 and one being full scarcity,
full competition between
the different user
of that region.