let's do as an example the life
cycle assessment input output
life cycle assessment of our paper towel
versus an electric dryer for hand drying.
So we just need to know the basic price.
So if a towel is about
two cents per towel,
we multiply it by the reference flow.
1.5 towel per functional unit.
If you remember.
And we get 0.0 $35 per functional unit.
Okay this is this is the main flow that
that we had for the electric dryer.
We know that the main flow
was the electricity and
at 10 cents per dollar or
$0.1 per kilowatt hour.
We multiply that by the amount
of kilowatt hour we
had perfection reference
flow which was 0.0
15 kilowatt hour, 1800 what time?
30 seconds.
And we get here 0.00
$15 per functional unit.
And we can start plugging it for
let's do a million of hand dried.
Okay.
And we can compare
the results with calculation
the Excel calculation we
did based on a coin vent.
Okay so let's look at the results of
this first for a million hand dried.
Okay.
And we have the paper towel
scenario paper towel mean
most of the money is invested in
the paper mill for a million hands dry.
That's the amount of dollar that we have.
Total c.
2 53 tons of co two If now I go not for
a million hand but a single pair of end.
I will get 53 tons divided by a million.
This is 53 graham C.
02 per pair of hand dried and
interestingly not surprisingly
the paper industry spend some as many
other company of the same sector.
But you see more surprisingly
the power generation and
supply is really important for this
paper and then you have some pulp mills,
truck transportation is important,
some pipeline transportation, coal mining.
Xterra.
That that that we have here because it's
also an energy intensive sector.
So 53 g of CO two per pair for and
right if now I apply my 0.0 $15 million.
Okay I get 14 ton of C.
02 and that means 14 g of C.
02 per pair of hands tried.
Okay so
this is about less than than a third
of the amount which was needed with paper
towel in this case again power generation,
he is really dominant and
the rest is much less.
But we still have spending in the coal
mining for the extraction of coal gas
is another source here and we'll get
some truck transportation here and
the natural gas distribution and
here's the spending were made in
the electricity sector which is power
generation and supply that we have here.
Very efficient way to get
results in a happy way.
Are they reliable?
They are hard to trace and and
we can raise questions but
it's really interesting
to identify whether all
the important sector were considered for
the process.
L.
C.
The other thing is in addition if you
go and we go to you can download and
have the full inventory here.
You will get some
services like lawyers and
other services, banking services etcetera,
which typically represent 1% or of any L.
C.
A.
And so you could you could use
in fact process input advocacy
to complement the processes
see on the services
to evaluate the emission
associated with these services.
So let's conclude in
summary input output I.
O. L. C.
A.
Takes advantage of free economic
data collected every year or
every five years by the Bureau
of Economic Analysis to
predict the economic intermediary flow and
the interest.
It has no cut off.
We all have all the spending in the other
400 and it covers the different services.
So very useful to check process
LCN test where the important
part of the supply chain have been
neglected like the airplane for
the computer which which
could be really important.
However, it's not possible
to differentiate product of
similar price within
a given industrial sector.
I cannot differentiate
two type of towels or
two types of computer if they
have a somewhat similar price.
So useful method you will also
find it in fact in cinema
pro when you will do your exercises,
you can in fact for
example add the services
using the seda database
that is available without in Singapore.
But you need to upload the input output
when you upload your different databases